Welcome to the chapter on cardiac pathology.
The first discussion is ischemic heart disease.
This is a group of syndromes.
We're gonna cover four in all
that are related to myocardial ischemia.
Remember that ischemia refers to a decrease
in blood flow to an organ.
It's usually due to atherosclerosis.
If you've got atherosclerosis in the coronary artery,
you decrease the amount of blood flow
going to the myocardium.
Therefore, the risk factors for ischemic heart disease
are gonna be very similar to those of atherosclerosis,
and it so happens that the incidence
of ischemic heart disease increases with age,
just as the incidence of atherosclerosis
also increases with age.
The first of these disorders is stable angina.
Angina refers to chest pain that is reversible.
The term stable here implies that the patient
does not have chest pain at rest,
but instead develops chest pain with exertion
or emotional stress.
The idea here is that if this is the coronary artery,
which is feeding the myocardium,
then the patients have atherosclerosis
of the coronary artery.
This then decreases the blood flow to the myocardium.
The patient would be fine at rest.
However, when there is exertion,
you won't be able to provide enough blood
to the myocardium, and hence there would be injury
to the myocardium resulting in chest pain.
Now, it's very high yield to note that when you get stable angina,
you have reversible injury to the myocytes.
So the cells do not die.
They simply undergo reversible injury.
And remember from chapter one of this text
that the hallmark of reversible injury is cellular swelling.
One more point to note is that when the patients have atherosclerosis,
they're only going to get angina when there's greater than 70% stenosis.
If there's less than 70% stenosis,
the patients are relatively asymptomatic, even with exertion.
When patients present with stable angina,
they'll have chest pain that radiates to the left arm or jaw.
Important to note that this chest pain will last less than 20 minutes.
Now, that's about the amount of time that the myocardium can withstand a lack of blood flow.
After that, you'd get irreversible injury and cell death.
And so the chest pain classically will last less than 20 minutes.
The patients may also have diaphoresis or sweating and shortness of breath.
Were an EKG to be performed, the EKG would show ST segment depression.
Now, the reason being is that here is the epicardium and then the myocardium and the endocardium.
Remember that these are the three layers of the heart, epicardium, myocardium, and endocardium.
The coronary arteries, they begin in the epicardium up here,
and then they eventually dive down in order to feed all three layers of the heart.
Now, if you decrease the amount of blood flow going through the coronary artery,
then this region here, right underneath the endocardium, is the most susceptible to ischemic damage.
And so that's exactly what's going to happen in stable angina.
You're going to get subendocardial right underneath the endocardium.
You're going to get subendocardial ischemia.
And the hallmark of subendocardial ischemia or damage on an EKG is ST segment depression.
Now, the chest pain in stable angina will be relieved by rest,
and that's because you decrease the demand of the myocardium by resting,
which then will decrease the amount of blood flow that needs to be provided to the myocardium.
Another way to relieve the chest pain would be nitroglycerin.
Remember that nitroglycerin has the ability to vasodilate both arteries and veins.
Its major mechanism of action is the vasodilation of veins,
which would then decrease the amount of blood that's returning to the heart.
And so then you would decrease the preload on the heart,
which would then decrease the stress on the myocardium of the heart.
Unstable angina is chest pain.
That's reversible, but it's unstable, i.e. it occurs at rest.
And this is due to rupture of the atherosclerotic plaque with thrombosis,
but an incomplete occlusion of a coronary artery, high yield, incomplete occlusion.
Here's the idea.
You've got a coronary artery going into the myocardium,
and this coronary artery has atherosclerosis.
Imagine if there's rupture, which would usually occur at the neck here or here,
then this would expose the subendothelial collagen and the necrotic material within the plaque,
which would then allow for activation of thrombosis.
Now thrombosis would occur, but it would only partially occlude this vessel.
That would then allow for a small amount of blood to flow through,
which would keep the myocardium alive.
However, the patient would have chest pain at rest.
Now again, important to note, you get incomplete occlusion.
That's super high yield.
And that this again would represent reversible injury to the myocytes.
On EKG, you would see ST-segment depression,
and that's because you would have predominantly subendocardial ischemia.
It's relieved by nitroglycerin.
Again, vasodilation would result in decreased preload,
which would then decrease the amount of work the myocardium had to do.
And there's a high risk of progression to MI.
Now imagine, here's an example where you can see a coronary artery.
Now there's been rupture of an atherosclerotic plaque,
and you can clearly see that there's a thrombus here.
Now this circumstance has a very high risk of progression to MI,
because it would be very easy for this thrombus to completely occlude the vessel.
And when you completely occlude the vessel,
that would then result in myocardial infarction.
The third type of angina, again, reversible chest pain,
is called prinzmental angina.
The idea here is that you get vasospasm of the coronary artery.
So again, here's the coronary artery.
This is going into the myocardium.
And you get vasospasm so that this artery clamps down.
Now when this artery clamps down,
it's going to completely cut the blood supply.
And that cutting of the blood supply will then result in episodes of chest pain
that are unrelated to exertion.
Whenever the vessel clamps down,
that's when the patient's going to have chest pain.
Now again, important to note that this still represents reversible injury to the myocytes.
We have not yet caused death of the myocytes.
And the EKG would show ST segment elevation.
Now the reason being is that if this is the epicardium,
this is the myocardium,
and this is the endocardium,
and what's happening here is that in the epicardium,
you've got the coronary artery,
and this is completely clamping down.
When this completely clamps down for a short period of time,
you will cut blood supply to the entire wall,
i.e. transmural.
And when you have transmural damage,
the classic finding is going to be ST segment elevation.
Now this would also be relieved by nitroglycerin,
which would decrease the preload on the heart.
In addition, calcium channel blockers can be used,
which would help to relieve the coronary artery vasospasm.
The next of the ischemic heart disease syndromes is myocardial infarction.
This is when you get necrosis of the cardiac myocytes,
so you get irreversible injury and cell death.
The classic way by which this occurs is rupture of an atherosclerotic plaque
with complete high yield,
with complete occlusion of the coronary artery.
So the idea here is that this is the coronary artery going into the heart.
You've got atherosclerosis.
You get rupture at the neck.
Now you get a complete thrombus,
and this complete thrombus blocks off the blood supply,
resulting in a lack of flow into the myocardium,
which will then result in death of the myocardium
after 20 minutes of lack of flow.
And so then you'd get necrosis of the cardiac myocytes.
Now other causes include coronary artery vasospasm.
If you had Prinsmetals angina that squeezed down
and shut down the blood vessel for greater than 20 minutes,
you'd get myocardial infarction.
Emboli can do this.
If there was an embolus that went into the coronary artery,
that would result in myocardial infarction.
Another important cause is vasculitis.
The classic example would be Kawasaki's disease.
Remember that that's a vasculitis that affects children
roughly around the age of five
and preferentially involves the coronary artery.
Now the idea here is that if you've got the coronary artery
going into the myocardium
and you have vasculitis or inflammation of this wall,
the inflammation would damage the endothelium,
exposing subendothelial collagen and tissue factor.
This would then allow for the coagulation cascade
to develop a thrombus which could then create
a myocardial infarction.
Here's a gross image of a coronary artery
reminding you of the fact that myocardial infarction
classically occurs when you have rupture
of an atherosclerotic plaque with complete occlusion.
Again, complete occlusion of the coronary artery
by thrombosis.
Clinically, patients who have myocardial infarction
will have severe crushing chest pain
that radiates to the left arm or jaw
and this time it's gonna last greater than 20 minutes.
And again, greater than 20 minutes implies
that you've now begun to cause necrosis
of the cardiac myocytes.
The patients will also have diaphoresis and dyspnea.
Dyspnea is due to the fact that the heart's not pumping
as well and so you're gonna get pulmonary congestion
and edema which is gonna result in dyspnea.
And of course, the symptoms would not be relieved
by nitroglycerin.
Myocardial infarction usually involves the left ventricle,
the right ventricle, and the atria are generally spared.
It's very important to note if we draw a picture
of the heart and cross section,
so this is the right ventricle,
this is the left ventricle,
this would be anterior and this would be posterior.
And so we've sorta just cut across the heart
and we've laid down a piece to look at
in this particular image.
Now, the most common artery involved
in myocardial infarction would be the left anterior descending
which would run somewhere here.
And remember that when you get occlusion
of the left anterior descending,
you're gonna get infarction of the anterior wall
of the ventricle along with the anterior portion
of the intraventricular septum.
The second most commonly involved coronary artery
would be the right coronary artery.
Remember that the right coronary artery would run here
and so when you get occlusion of the right coronary artery,
you're gonna get infarction of the posterior wall
of the left ventricle
and the posterior portion of the intraventricular septum.
And finally the third artery that could be involved
would be the left circumflex
and occlusion of this artery would give you infarction
of the lateral wall of the left ventricle.
And so these are some key arteries that can be involved
with the distribution in which you would see a disease.
When a patient has a myocardial infarction,
the very initial phase of involvement is subendocardial
involving less than 50% of the myocardial thickness.
The idea here is if you've got the endocardium,
the myocardium, and the epicardium,
of course the coronary artery is sitting here
in the epicardium and will be feeding the wall in this manner.
And so the most distal portion from the beginning
of the coronary artery, which is over here in the endocardium,
will be the first to necrose.
And so initially patients will have subendocardial necrosis,
classically involving less than 50% of the wall.
Now, if an EKG were to be done at this point,
it would show ST segment depression.
Again, when you damage the subendocardial region,
you get ST segment depression.
With continued ischemia, this necrosis will progress
and will involve the entire wall,
and that's called a transmural infarction.
Transmural infarctions are the most common type of infarction.
And in this particular case,
you would now see ST segment elevation on the EKG,
and that's because you see ST segment elevation
when you have damage to the entire wall,
as we've already mentioned earlier.
When you want to make a diagnosis of myocardial infarction,
looking for cardiac enzymes in the blood can be very helpful.
Again, the idea here is that you're looking to see
whether there's been irreversible damage to the myocytes,
which is the definition of myocardial infarction.
And when there's irreversible damage to the myocytes,
you know that the hallmark is going to be membrane damage,
and with the membrane damage,
the enzymes that are present within the cardiac myocytes
will leak out into the blood.
And so, if you can find them in the blood,
that tells you that the patient had a myocardial infarction.
The most sensitive and specific marker is troponin I.
This rises two to four hours after infarction,
peaks at 24 hours, and stays high for seven to 10 days.
And so, this really is the best marker.
Another useful marker can be CKMB.
Now, this is useful because it rises quickly,
however, it also goes down relatively quickly.
And so, let's say a patient has an infarction,
and then five days later, develops another infarction,
which can occur, and it's a complication of myocardial infarction.
If you were looking to prove that you had a second infarction,
you wouldn't be able to do so with troponin I,
because troponin I would go up and then stay up
for seven to 10 days.
And so, one potentially useful marker would be CKMB.
And again, the reason being is that it would have gone down
after 72 hours, and if there's a re-infarction,
it will then rise again.
And so, CKMB is particularly useful for detecting re-infarction
a few days after an initial MI.
The treatment for myocardial infarction is aspirin and heparin.
The goal here is to limit additional thrombosis.
Recall that it was the complete occlusion of the coronary artery
by thrombosis that led to the MI,
and so we want to limit the thrombosis.
Supplemental oxygen is given to minimize ischemia.
Nitrates are given with the goal of vasodilating both arteries and veins.
Of course, the major mechanism would be dilatation of the veins,
which would decrease the preload on the heart,
which would then decrease the stress on the heart.
Beta blockers are useful because they slow the heart rate,
and when you slow the heart rate,
you decrease the demand for oxygen,
and you also decrease the risk for arrhythmia.
And arrhythmia is a feared complication very early after MI occurs.
The final treatment listed here would be an ACE inhibitor.
The idea of the ACE inhibitor is that you want to decrease the left ventricular dilatation.
Basically, remember that ACE inhibitors are going to block the production of angiotensin II.
Now, of course, angiotensin II does two things.
Number one, it causes constriction of the peripheral arterioles,
and so therefore, by giving an ACE inhibitor,
you'll block that constriction of the peripheral arterioles,
therefore decreasing the afterload on the heart.
And in addition, remember that angiotensin II goes to the adrenal and causes release of aldosterone,
which eventually comes back to the kidney and grabs sodium, and then water will follow.
So you would increase the blood volume via angiotensin II, and by giving an ACE inhibitor,
you'll decrease that effect so that the blood volume will not increase.
All of this acts to decrease the risk of left ventricular dilatation.
A more definitive treatment would be fibrinolysis or angioplasty.
Remember that the myocardial infarction was due to thrombosis,
and so fibrinolysis would destroy the thrombus.
Now, when you perform fibrinolysis or angioplasty,
that's going to result in a return of blood flow to an area of dead heart,
and so that's going to produce two interesting complications.
The first is called contraction band necrosis,
and the idea here is that if this is the dead myocyte and you return blood,
when you return blood, you're going to return calcium.
So calcium will enter into the cell, and when calcium enters into the cell,
it's going to cause contraction of the muscle fibers within the cell,
and that contraction is then going to result in these dense pink lines within the cells
called contraction bands.
And so here's an image here just to highlight that.
This is an area of dead heart.
You can see that you've got myocytes with no nuclei.
Notice that, for example, this is a myocyte,
and there is no nucleus, indicating that the cell is dead.
However, also notice that you've got these pink bands running up and down the cell,
and this is called contraction bands,
and this occurs when you return calcium back to the dead tissue.
Of course, the calcium then enters the cell and causes contraction of the muscle.
Another interesting complication of returning blood back to the dead tissue
will be that you can get reperfusion injury.
Now, the idea here is that when you return blood, you're returning oxygen,
and the oxygen can then result in the generation of free radicals.
The free radicals can then further injure the myocardium,
and that's called a reperfusion injury.
The way this would present is that you've got a patient who,
for example, has an elevated level of cardiac enzymes.
You then go in and open up the blocked blood vessel,
and then after you open the blocked vessel,
the cardiac enzymes continue to rise.
And so examiners can ask you what's going on,
and the answer is that this is an example of reperfusion injury.
When you gave back blood, you gave back oxygen,
and the oxygen eventually resulted in the formation of free radicals,
which then further damaged the myocardium.
Again, reperfusion injury is very high yield.
Now, the last discussion concerning myocardial infarction
essentially involves both the microscopic and the gross changes
that would occur after the infarction,
along with the complications that you can see clinically
that are basically a result of these changes.
And this is a very high yield table,
so I just want to spend a couple of minutes going over it.
The first thing I'd like to remind you of
is just a general principle.
We're really going to focus here on these microscopic changes,
and everything else will be a derivative of that.
Let's go back and remind ourselves
from the global picture of ischemia and necrosis,
that the first thing that's going to happen
when you cut the blood supply to the cells and the cells die
is you're going to get coagulative necrosis.
Now, coagulative necrosis basically implies
that you're going to remove the nucleus from the cell.
Remember that the hallmark of the dead cell
is removal of the nucleus,
and so you're going to get pycnosis,
cariorexis, and cariolisis.
And that is going to be your sign of coagulative necrosis.
So that's the first thing that's going to happen.
The second thing that's going to happen
is that acute inflammation always follows necrosis.
And so you're going to bring in neutrophils and macrophages.
Now, after you get acute inflammation,
which is going to clean up all of the dead tissue,
the next phase will be healing.
And because the heart is a permanent tissue,
you're not going to be able to regenerate the heart.
Instead, you're going to form scar.
And remember that the foundation of scar is granulation tissue.
And so the next phase will be granulation tissue,
and then finally the granulation tissue will be converted to a scar.
So again, three key phases.
Coagulative necrosis, inflammation, and healing.
Now, the next point is that you have to understand
when each of these phases is going to occur.
Now, the way by which I like to remember this
is to simply remember one day, one week, one month.
And so what's going to happen?
For the first day, you're going to get coagulative necrosis.
After that first day, then you're going to get inflammation
for up to one week.
And the inflammation will begin with neutrophils
and then progress to macrophages.
And after one week, you're going to get granulation tissue.
And then it's going to take one month
for that granulation tissue to be converted to scar.
All right, so one day, one week, one month.
And those are the key sort of dividers of the major phases
that are going to occur during the process.
Now, with that in mind, let's look at the chart.
So what do we say?
We say that for the first 24 hours,
the key thing that's going to happen is coagulative necrosis.
Now, during the first four hours,
you really don't get any changes at all.
There are no microscopic changes,
hence there will be no gross changes.
The key complication during that first four hours
is going to be cardiogenic shock.
If you have a massive infarction,
the heart will completely fail
and you'll get loss of blood supply to the vital organs,
which is basically called shock.
Again, inability to maintain systemic blood pressure
with lack of blood flow to vital organs.
So that's the one complication in that first four hours.
Another complication that can arise in that first four hours
is you can get congestive heart failure,
which is when blood begins to back up
and is not being pumped forward well.
And so the hallmark of that is a decreased ejection fraction.
And the final complication would be arrhythmia.
Arrhythmia is an early complication that occurs in that first day.
Now, after the first four hours,
you're going to begin the process of coagulative necrosis,
and that's going to take one day.
Again, the hallmark of coagulative necrosis
will be pycnosis, cariorexis, cariolysis,
and what you're going to see on gross exam
will be dark discoloration of the heart.
Now, the key complication in that first 24 hours
when you've got the initial injury
along with the coagulative necrosis will be arrhythmia.
And basically, the idea here is that if you've damaged
the conducting systems of the heart,
it's going to become evident in that first 24 hours
when the cells are dying.
And if it doesn't happen in the first 24 hours,
it'd be less likely to occur as you move forward
because if you've damaged it, you've damaged it,
and you would see it within the first 24 hours.
Now, of course, at the milestone of one day,
the next thing that's going to happen over the next week
is going to be acute inflammation.
Remember that from one day to one week,
you're going to have acute inflammation.
The very initial phase of that will be neutrophils,
and they'll come in from day one to day three,
and then the macrophages will come in
from day four to day seven.
Now, just focusing on these two,
the key gross change will be that you have
white blood cells within the myocardium,
and the white blood cells within the myocardium
will result in a yellow pallor.
So, during this entire inflammatory phase,
the gross change will be yellow pallor.
Now, the key complications based on this microscopic change
will be dependent on what cell is there.
So, for example, when the neutrophils are there,
the main complication is going to be
fibrinous pericarditis.
Now, the idea here is that if you've got your endocardium,
you've got a myocardium,
and then you've got the epicardium,
when you get transmural infarction,
you've killed off the entire wall,
then when the neutrophils come in,
the neutrophils will come in
and inflame this entire wall.
Now, in addition, some of that inflammatory exudate
will actually go out into the pericardium,
which surrounds the epicardium,
and so you'll also get pericarditis
during that day one to day three period.
And the key issue here is that that pericarditis
will present with chest pain and a friction rub.
Now, important to note that you'd only get
fibrinous pericarditis with a transmural infarction
when the entire wall was involved.
If the infarction was subendocardial,
where it didn't go up into the epicardium,
of course, you wouldn't have inflammatory debris
going into the pericardium,
and so, therefore, you wouldn't get
fibrinous pericarditis.
Now, after that is going to be the macrophage phase.
And the key reason the macrophages come in
is to eat up all of the dead and necrotic debris.
Now, when the macrophages eat up
all of the dead and necrotic debris,
that is the time that the wall is going to be weakest.
And so, what's the key complication
during the macrophage phase?
Rupture.
That's the single word you want to remember.
And so, for example,
if you had infarction of the ventricular free wall,
that could rupture, resulting in cardiac tamponade.
Again, the idea here is that if this is the heart,
right, and you've got the left ventricle here.
Let's put this to the left atrium,
the right atrium, and the right ventricle.
If you have infarction here of this ventricular free wall,
and this ruptures, of course,
the heart is surrounded by this pericardium.
Blood would go into the pericardium
and would begin to compress the heart,
and that would result in something called cardiac tamponade.
And so, that's one of the complications of rupture.
Another complication of rupture would be to rupture
the intraventricular septum leading to a shunt.
So, again, if this is your four chambers of the heart,
and this is the right ventricle and left ventricle,
and you've got an infarction here,
if this ruptures, you're now going to create an opening
between the right and left ventricle,
and that could result in shunting of blood
from the left ventricle to the right ventricle.
In addition, you can get rupture of a papillary muscle,
and this would lead to mitral insufficiency.
Here, just illustrating this,
here again is your left ventricle.
Remember that the mitral valve has these strings
that come from it called the cordae,
and the cordae attached to the papillary muscle,
and the papillary muscle helps to close this mitral valve.
If you rupture this papillary muscle,
you're not going to be able to pull close this valve,
and so you're going to get insufficiency
with blood going backwards during systole,
and so that would be an example of mitral insufficiency
with rupture of a papillary muscle.
Very high yield to remember that the papillary muscle
is fed by the right coronary artery,
and so therefore it's with occlusion
of the right coronary artery
that you're going to have the risk
of rupture of the papillary muscle.
Now of course, the next phase will be granulation tissue.
After the macrophages come in,
you've got to then create the base for the scar,
and the scaffold or the base for the scar
is called granulation tissue.
So granulation tissue, its hallmark will be
plump fibroblasts, collagen, and blood vessels.
Now because there are so many blood vessels,
what you're going to see on gross examination
is a red border coming in from the outside of the dead tissue.
Now the reason it comes in from the outside
of the dead tissue is the following.
If this is the area of necrosis,
then the blood vessels are going to come
from the normal tissue out here
and begin to grow into the area of necrosis
to form the granulation tissue.
And so initially what you're going to see
is a red border to the area of the dead tissue,
and that is going to be the hallmark of granulation tissue.
And so that's why we say here
that when granulation tissue comes in,
you'll see a red border emerging from the edge of the infarct.
Now the final stage is that the granulation tissue
will be converted to fibrosis or a scar.
And so what you're going to see on gross exam
will be a white scar.
Now recall that the scar is not as strong as the myocardium.
So you took away myocardium and you put in place a scar.
So because now you've weakened the wall of the ventricle,
that's going to increase the risk for aneurysm
or balloon-like dilatation of the ventricular wall.
Once you've got a scar,
you're not going to have good movement of the wall.
And in addition,
if you have an aneurysm,
that's only going to further complicate
the fact that you're going to have stasis along that wall.
So that's going to increase the risk of a mural thrombus
or a thrombus forming along the wall of the scar.
And finally, one complication that can arise is called Dressler's syndrome.
Now this is a very rare complication,
but it does show up on board exams,
so I want to briefly discuss it.
The idea here is that if you had a transmural infarction
and you had inflammation within the pericardium,
that inflammation in the pericardium could expose
the pericardial antigens to the immune system.
This could then theoretically result in the formation of antibodies
against the pericardium.
Now if you formed antibodies against your own pericardium,
you'd get an autoimmune pericarditis, and that would happen,
for example, six weeks or eight weeks after an infarction
when the immune system had enough time to actually generate those antibodies,
and that is called Dressler's syndrome.
It is a pericarditis that arises six to eight weeks after infarction
due to a autoimmune phenomena where you begin to produce antibodies
against your own pericardium.
Again, that is Dressler's syndrome,
and that is very high yield for the board exams.
Alright, now let's use a series of images
that is present within your text in order to review
some of these high yield principles.
Here's an example of a heart that has undergone a myocardial infarction.
You can clearly see that there is dark discoloration of the myocardium,
and so we would expect to see dark discoloration from four hours to 24 hours.
And of course, what's happening microscopically
is that we're getting coagulative necrosis from four hours to 24 hours.
Now also you can note that in this particular case,
here is the thickness of the myocardium,
and you can see that the myocardium is only partially involved.
And so in this particular case,
we only have a subendocardial infarction,
at least focally within this image.
Here's a microscopic image showing an infarction.
These are the myocytes,
and you can see that there are no nuclei within the myocytes.
So the fact that the nuclei have been removed indicates that we are,
indicates that coagulative necrosis has occurred.
And of course, coagulative necrosis would occur from four to 24 hours.
Now notice that we don't have any neutrophils here,
and so therefore, we're in that four to 24 hour window.
Now after coagulative necrosis,
the next thing that will happen is that the neutrophils will come in.
And of course, the neutrophils come in from day one to day three,
and the key complication after the neutrophils come in,
will be that we can develop fibrinous pericarditis.
And that's because the inflammation can spread into the pericardium,
resulting in all of this fibrin or inflammatory debris
on the surface of the heart.
So notice that you can kind of see this shaggy appearance to the surface of the heart.
This represents fibrinous pericarditis.
Of course, very high yield to know that fibrinous pericarditis would only occur
with a transmural infarction, and you would not see it with a subendocardial infarction.
Now eventually, the next thing that will happen is that the macrophages will come in.
And of course, they come in from day four to day seven.
The key complication when the macrophages come in will be rupture.
And so in this particular case, you can see that we've ruptured the free wall of the ventricle,
and so this again would be day four to day seven.
Here's an example where we ruptured the papillary muscle.
Here are the corda tendinae that connect the papillary muscle to the mitral valve.
We've ruptured here the papillary muscle.
Remember that the papillary muscle is fed by the right coronary artery.
And again, because this rupture has occurred, we know that we are day four to day seven.
Of course, after the macrophages come in from one week to one month, we'll have granulation tissue.
And after one month, we'll eventually develop a scar.
And so here you can see a white scar present within the myocardium.
Microscopic examination of that scar would simply reveal dense collagen.
And remember that the key collagen present within the scar is going to be type one collagen.
Now, of course, because you've got a scar instead of myocardium, the wall is potentially weak.
And so over time, that wall can develop a balloon-like dilatation, resulting in a ventricular aneurysm.
And here you can see that we've created a balloon-like dilatation.
You can see that the ventricle is dilated, and again, that is a ventricular aneurysm.
One complication of both scar and aneurysm would be that we could form a neural thrombus
along the wall of the scar or the aneurysm.
The third syndrome of ischemic heart disease is sudden cardiac death.
This is when you get unexpected death due to cardiac disease.
Generally, it would occur without symptoms or with less than one hour of symptoms.
And it's usually due to a fatal ventricular arrhythmia.
And so you get sudden death either without symptoms or very shortly after the onset of symptoms.
The most common etiology is acute ischemia.
Ninety percent of these patients would have pre-existing severe atherosclerosis.
Other causes would include mitral valve prolapse.
That can result in sudden cardiac death.
Cardiomyopathy can result in sudden cardiac death.
And so can cocaine abuse with vasospasm related to cocaine.
But again, most commonly, we would expect to have atherosclerosis.
The fourth and final ischemic heart disease is called chronic ischemic heart disease.
The idea here is that you get poor myocardial function due to chronic ischemic damage.
Now, you don't have to necessarily have infarction.
It can be with or without infarction.
But you have chronic ischemia which slowly damages the myocardium.
This can then progress to congestive heart failure.
And we're going to talk about congestive heart failure in the next section.
And so this concludes our discussion of ischemic heart disease.
So this concludes our discussion of ischemic heart disease.